<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Remonstrance, manifesting the lamentable miseries of the creditors and servants of the late King, Queen, &amp; Prince. Who vvith great sums purchas'd their places during their lives, and receiving no benefit therof, since 1639. did for a long time expect an agreement between the King and Parliament. But the event proving otherwise, they by that occasion losing their places, and therewith the only means of their subsistence; therefore the late Parliament in consideration thereof, by an Act June 1649. ordained, that they should be satisfied of all their just debts due before these wars, out of the goods and personal estate of the late King, Queen, and Prince: of which also they were exceedingly frustrated, for 28000 l. in ready mony, and about 40000 l. worth of the said goods were taken from their use, and many of the said goods are still in the use of particular men, whilst many of the said creditors and servants begg, and starve forwant [sic] of bread. Yet the survivers, with the widows and orphans of the rest deceased, have just cause to hope, that his Excellency the Lord Gen. Cromwell, Major Gen. Harrison, and others, who were instrumentall in procuring the said Act, will likewise in all reason, equity, and compassion see it fulfilled; seeing God hath given them power, authority, and opportunity to do many such just, and needfull acts, for preventing the ruin of hundreds of poor families, which otherwise would speedily follow.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92429</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866124</idno>
  <idno type="VID">118388</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240945041</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing R986</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E693_13</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207048</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866124</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99866124e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92429)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118388)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 107:E693[13])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Remonstrance, manifesting the lamentable miseries of the creditors and servants of the late King, Queen, &amp; Prince. Who vvith great sums purchas'd their places during their lives, and receiving no benefit therof, since 1639. did for a long time expect an agreement between the King and Parliament. But the event proving otherwise, they by that occasion losing their places, and therewith the only means of their subsistence; therefore the late Parliament in consideration thereof, by an Act June 1649. ordained, that they should be satisfied of all their just debts due before these wars, out of the goods and personal estate of the late King, Queen, and Prince: of which also they were exceedingly frustrated, for 28000 l. in ready mony, and about 40000 l. worth of the said goods were taken from their use, and many of the said goods are still in the use of particular men, whilst many of the said creditors and servants begg, and starve forwant [sic] of bread. Yet the survivers, with the widows and orphans of the rest deceased, have just cause to hope, that his Excellency the Lord Gen. Cromwell, Major Gen. Harrison, and others, who were instrumentall in procuring the said Act, will likewise in all reason, equity, and compassion see it fulfilled; seeing God hath given them power, authority, and opportunity to do many such just, and needfull acts, for preventing the ruin of hundreds of poor families, which otherwise would speedily follow.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[5], 11 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 23".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Debt cancellation --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118388:1"/>
            <p>A REMONSTRANCE, Manifesting the lamentable Miseries of the Creditors and Servants of the late <hi>KING, QƲEEN, &amp; PRINCE.</hi> WHO With great sums purchas'd their places during their lives, and receiving no benefit ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, since 1639. did for a long time expect an Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment between the King and Parliament.</p>
            <p>But the event proving otherwise, they by that occasion losing their places, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the only means of their subsistence; therefore the late Parliament in consideration thereof, by an Act <hi>June</hi> 1649. ordained, That they should be satisfied of all their just debts due before these Wars, out of the goods and personal Estate of the late King, Queen, and Prince:</p>
            <p>Of which also they were exceedingly frustrated, for 28000 l. in ready mony, and about 40000 l. worth of the said goods were taken from their use, and many of the said goods are still in the use of particular men, whilst many of the said Creditors and Servants begg, and starve forwant of Bread.</p>
            <p>Yet the survivers, with the widows and orphans of the rest deceased, have just cause to hope, that his Excellency the Lord Gen. <hi>Cromwell,</hi> Major Gen. <hi>Harrison,</hi> and others, who were instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall in procuring the said Act, will likewise in all reason, equity, and compassion see it fulfilled; see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God hath given them power, authority, and opportunity to do many such just, and need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full acts, for preventing the ruin of hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of poor families, which otherwise would speedily follow.</p>
            <p>London, Printed in the Year, 1653.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:118388:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118388:2"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onsidering the great, grievous, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold sufferings of the Creditors and Servants, with the widows and Orphans of others deceased, heretofore of the late King, Queen, and Prince, which have been occasioned by the great injustice, tedious delays, and unexpected obstructions which they have found in the way of prosecution for those debts and wages, almost these four years space, they expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting (upon good grounds both in regard of their own right, and the late Parliaments Acts in order to their satisfaction) to have received payment of those debts long before this time, out of the product from sale of the late King, Queen, and Princes goods, and personall estate, at least so far as the proceed thereof would ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, as more at large by the Act of Parliament of the 26 June 1649. in that behalf is appointed.</p>
            <p>Next, considering the great pains, charges, troubles, attendance, and losses both of time and other urgent af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, unto which the Trustees appointed by the said Act, for sale of the foresaid goods and personal estate, have not only been necessitated, but likewise exposed to the disobligation, hazards, vexations, and reproaches of those Creditors and Servants, and otherwise, which by reason and occasion of their dissatisfaction, although by the said Trustees not in the least deserved, it not being in their power to give either better or speedier satisfaction to the said Creditors and Servants then they
<pb facs="tcp:118388:3"/>have done from time to time; And instead of the said Trustees reaping any such advantage by their places, as by some ignorant people hath been maliciously repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, it hath proved a great losse unto such of them as have great imployments otherwise, their allowance not exceeding 7 d. in the pound to be equally divided amongst them, being ten in number, and out of which they are to defray all incident charges whatsoever of their Officers and assistants.</p>
            <p>Which hath proved very great unto them, not only in going a Committee of three or more of them upon all needfull occasions to <hi>Tudbury, Ludlow,</hi> the Isle of <hi>Wight, Holmby, Theobalds, Windsor,</hi> and severall o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places, they being by the said Act of Parliament thereunto enjoyned, but likewise in removing and trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting of goods at their own charges; and besides, in regard of the aforesaid delays, the said Trustees have been forced to attend upon this imployment about the space of four years, which otherwise possibly might have been finished in two years, if the said Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament had not been so powerfully contradicted: So that all incident charges being deducted, unto which they have been thus necessarily occasioned, the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said allowance will not amount to 80 li.<hi>per. annum</hi> for each of them, even for the time past, they not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how much time, charge, attendance, hinderance, loss, or other prejudice or trouble the time to come may produce.</p>
            <p>And also considering the divided estate and conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on wherein the aforesaid Creditors and Servants now stand, they being (for the most part) only sensible that they are great sufferers, and that their present conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is so lamentable, that through not being satisfied of the said debts, whereof they ought to have been timely
<pb facs="tcp:118388:3"/>relieved, many of them have been starved, even for want of bread, and others of them not able any longer to subsist without the meer charity of some compassio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate friends and neighbours, and yet none of them able to propound nor find out an effectuall expedient for their present relief, the rather in that they are for the most part ignorant, of the grounds and reasons of such their sad &amp; deplorable afflictions, saving only that they did not proceed of any misdemeanours in themselves.</p>
            <p>Therefore, I have here in this short Treatise, out of a tender respect to those my distressed Countrymen, take occasion to represent their grievous necessities, and pinching extremities, to the view of all those who are in authority, and in all conscience, equity, and reason, bound so to sympathize their condition, as with all pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible speed to fullfill and make compleat what the late Parliament did delay, withdraw and neglect: and in order thereunto, I make some use of mine own expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, which I have had concerning the grounds and reasons of those distressed peoples grievous sufferings. With which for their more speedy help (I suppose) then other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, I do here make them acquainted, that they unanimously, peaceably, and discreetly, using the easie means and ways unto which they are here advised, may with Gods assistance reap a fruitfull successe upon those their mutuall labours; and for my part, if for this my tender zeal and care for their good, I be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deficient or super-aboundant upon severall and respective occasions in this discourse, I hope that their own judgments &amp; reason, with theirs also, who carefully read what here I write, will moderate such usuall extreams in most men; and in token of my fervent wishes to their good successe in this so long ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed business, (I hope) that my earnest prayers to God shall not be wanting in their behalf, to effect and crown these my weak endeavours, in order to procure them some speedy relief, and thereby to prevent the starving of some, and ruine of many, which otherwise (in all humane sense) will undoubtedly follow.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118388:4"/>
            <head>A Remonstrance, manifesting the lamentable miseries of the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors and Servants of the late King, Queen and Prince, who with great sums pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chas'd their places during their lives, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving no benefit thereof since 1639, did for, a long time expect an agreement between the King and Parliament, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Act of Parliament of the</hi> 26 <hi>of</hi> June 1649. <hi>doth ordain and declare, That the Goods, and Personal Estate of the late King, Queen, and Prince, shall be exposed to sale, and that the money Arising thereby shall be Imployed and Disposed of, towards the Satisfaction of the debts due from the late King, Queen and Prince, before the late Wars, unto their Servants and Creditors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is also thereby Enacted, That the Councell of State shall within</hi> 14 <hi>dayes after the Return to them of any Duplicate of the said goods from the Trustees in the said Act named, make choice of such particulars of the said goods, as they shall think fit to be reserved for uses of State, not exceeding the value of</hi> 10000 <hi>li and with all convenient speed to report, or certifie the same to the Parliament, to the end they may receive their approbation or dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>approbation thereupon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And it is thereby farther Enacted, That</hi> 30000 <hi>li. out of the first money to be raised by sale of the said goods, shall be lent to Treasurers of the Navy, and to be reimbursed and restored by the said Treasurers, by the first day of May</hi> 1650. <hi>unto the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surers for sale of the said goods, for the uses in the said Act ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in obedience to the said Act of Parliament, the Treasu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118388:4"/>for sale of the said goods did lend unto the said Treasurers of the Navy, the sum of 26500 <hi>li.</hi> out of the first money raised by sail of the said goods, which is not yet repayed or restored either in whole, or in part, the said Act of Parliament not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding; so that by the said Act of Parliament it being ordained, That the goods and personal Estate of the late King Queen and Prince, shall be sold towards the payment of their debts due before the War, and to persons that are not Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents, so far as the product will extend; therefore the said Creditors and Servants were encouraged to make Application unto the Trustees named in the same Act, for to receive and state their Accounts in order to a satisfaction, as by the said Act of Parliament more at large, is directed and appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            <p>And the said Trustees certified to the Parliament for their approbation and allowance a List of about 120 of such of the said Creditors, Servants, Widdows and Orphans, as they conceived had most need, and at that time had brought in their Accounts, and by order of Parliament of the 14th of <hi>March</hi> 1649. not only made payment to them of 12800 l. but also made a second List, containing about 970 of other of the said Creditors &amp; Servants, and presented the same to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament about the 3. of <hi>Jan.</hi> 1650. at which time the Councel of State had by vertue of diverse Orders, directed to the Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stees and Contractors for sale of the said goods, reserved and furnished all places then in publique use, with about 16000 l. worth of the said goods, yet neverthelesse the goods at that time undisposed of, were more than sufficient to have satisfied the said second List, by above 29000 l. and did then beleeve that according to the Act of Parliament in that behalf made, the 26500 l. lent the Navy would have been repaid.</p>
            <p>But the said Trustees did (day after day) attend the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from the beginning of <hi>Jan.</hi> to the beginning of <hi>August</hi> following, before the said second list was allowed; in the which interim of time the Additional Act was passed, which doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, <hi>That the words Goods and personal Estate, mentioned in an Act for sale of the Goods and personal Estate of the late King, Queen and Prince, shall be deemed, and taken to extend only unto all jewels, plate, furs, hangings, statues, meddals, pictures, ward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>robestuff,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118388:5"/>and all other housholdstuff and utensils whatsoever, and to all Libraries, the Library of</hi> James-<hi>house, with all Meddals, Rings, Globes, and Mathematical Instruments in the said Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brary only Excepted;</hi> by which limitation and restriction there is in all probability taken from the use of the said Servants and Creditors, above 100000 l. which those words, <hi>Goods and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonal Estate</hi> for the first Act comprised would have compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended: And doth also contrary to the said first Act, reserve 10000 l. worth of the said goods, more than is thereby ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, and the Library of <hi>James</hi>'s, which contains the Libra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of <hi>Whitehall</hi> and <hi>Richmond,</hi> in all worth about 6000 l. and doth discharge the 26500 l. lent as before for the uses of the Navy, and giveth no security for any of the aforesaid sums, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise then for the sum of 25918 l. 1 s. 4 d. out of any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed Real or Personal estate, not in charge in the Exchequer, nor formerly granted by Authority of Parliament, and the said additional Act is much wanting in prescribing a certain Rule how to proceed in such discoveries.</p>
            <p>This Act being passed, the said List was allowed, and an Order sent therewith, containing directions for the Payment thereof as followeth.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>Exchequer Chamber, <date>
                           <hi>Wednesday</hi> 13 Aug. 1651.</date> At the Committee for the Creditors and Servants of the late King, Queen and Prince.</dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By vertue of an Order of Parliament dated the</hi> 22 <hi>day of</hi> July 1651. <hi>It is ordered by this Committee that it be referred to the Contractors and Trustees appointed by act of Parliament for sale of the late King, Queen and Princes goods to make payment of several sums mentioned and comprised in a List of the said Debtors, and Debts, reported to, and allowed by the Parliament, and the said Trustees &amp; Contractors are hereby directed to make payment of the said severall sums respectively, either in ready money or by goods, according to the apprisement of the said goods, not allowing the same, or any part thereof, for a lower and a les<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serrate than they are apprised at.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>William Stephens, James Challanor, Richard Lucy, Lu. Hodges Tho. Jervase, Gregory Clements.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>At which time the Councel of State sent their Order to the Trustees and Contractors for sale of the said goods, to require
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118388:5"/>them not to expose to sale any of the said goods undisposed of, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til they had made their choice out of the same, according unto the Acts of Parliament in that behalf made, and referred the care thereof unto a Committee, who made choice out of the said goods of the most vendible thereof, to about 49000 l. as by the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar paper which was by two of that Committee brought unto the said Trustees, containing the particulars of such their Choice, but refused to set their hands thereunto, (according to the first Act) to whom the said Trustees declared, That there was not goods left to satisfy the said second List, more than what they had reserved, by at least 10000 l. to which they replyed, that they hoped the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel would forthwith discharge a great part of the said goods.</p>
            <p>By all which premises it appeareth, that the said additional Act in stead of contributing an enlargement to the relief of the said Creditors and Servants, as by them and others was expected, who at that time had waited in order thereto above two years; But contrary thereunto it tended to the ruin of many of them, in that it did cut off the best hopes of Relief for the 970 persons containd in the said second List, and left nothing to satisfie above 400 per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons more not yet inserted in any List, but what may be produced by way of discovery. Amongst whom, with the rest of the said Creditors, there is yet due about 90000 l. most of the persons con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the said second List being allowed but the one half of their said debts.</p>
            <p>And notwithstanding there is taken away by the limitation of the first Act as aforesaid, above 100000 l. yet also there is taken away in ready money for the use of the Navy, 26500 l. Reserved in goods, more than by the first Act is appointed, about 39000 l. And paid to Colonell <hi>Downs,</hi> by Order of Parliament in ready mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, 1500 l. All which doe amount unto the sum of 67000 l.</p>
            <p>And yet neverthelesse there are diverse goods which are not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served, but sold to the Creditors, which as yet they cannot receive, as the Statues in <hi>Whitehall</hi> garden, hangings, &amp;c. in use at the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament house, for the Entertainment of Embassadors; all which have also occasiond the delay of the said servants, &amp;c. And therfore the Trustees could not make them better satisfaction otherwise than with what was left to do it withall, the mony being first taken away, and afterwards the best of the goods: The said Creditors then seeing their great hopes like to produce so little effect, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stractions
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118388:6"/>growing on by the <hi>Scotch</hi> Kings coming into <hi>England,</hi> did desire, that the remaining goods left, might be distributed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst them, and accordingly the Contractors, with the assistance of several of the said Creditors, did to the best of their skill equally divide all the said goods into Dividends, which were drawn by lot, &amp; so made payment of the said List in goods to about 73000 l. and to above 400 of men, widows and orphans, who were not able to accept of goods, in ready money to the sum of 7500 l. which in effect, with what hath been takē &amp; paid as aforesaid, is the total of all the goods as have come to the Cognizance of the said Trustees, and there is still unpaid of the said second List, about 10000 l.</p>
            <p>So that if the said Act of Parliament of the 29 of June 1649. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from the Supreme Authority of the Nation, who put the late King to death for breach of Lawes, Covenants and Trust, was not a perfect security to the said Creditors and Servants, for pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their said debts out of the product of the said goods, and personal Estates of the late King, Queen, and Prince, and a just ground of incouragement for them to rely thereupon, then what better hopes could any people of this Nation have had towards the Injoyment of any Privileges or Estates belonging to them, by Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of any Acts of Parliament, had they continued, and their Session not been turned into a Cessation (the said Act passing away the said Goods and Personal Estate from the Commonwealth) and doth invest the property thereof in trustees for the use of the said Creditors; and yet neverthelesse by a Collateral Act, and Orders, so to dispose therof, as that almost nothing therof, as yet, hath come to the said Creditors and Servants, in Comparison of that which justly would by them have been received had the said first act of Parliament continued in full force and power? By all which most of the said Creditors are much worse than before, some of them ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, during their attendance starved for want of bread, others of them are no longer able to subsist, they as yet having received no relief, and the rest generally not much bettered, in that what they have so received doth produce so little, their debts being great, and themselves much indebted, and therefore necessitated to sell at any rate; and made much more poor by reason of so tedious an atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, and now their Creditors are more cruell than before.</p>
            <p>After all which, many of the said Creditors being willing to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt all lawfull means for the recovery of their said debts, did in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118388:6"/>pursuance of the said Additionall Act of Parliament, inquire, and have found out, that there are great quantities of Linnen, and other rich things, appertaining to the late Queen, of which as yet no account hath been given, some few of her Chapell Vestments having been already discovered.</p>
            <p>Others for great quantities of the late Kings plate, have not as yet accounted for concealment thereof according to the said Additio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Act.</p>
            <p>Another for a rich Jewel of the Lady <hi>Elizabeth's</hi> deceased; worth about 1500 l. the Trustees proceedings therein being almost 2 year since stopped by Order of the House till farther Order. Q. When will that be?</p>
            <p>Another for goods at <hi>Vaux</hi>-hall, worth about 200 li. and one who desired to have an interest therein, upon making a grievous complaint, obtained an Order of Parliament, requiring the Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stees to carry the said goods back from <hi>Somerset</hi> house unto <hi>Vaux</hi>-hall, without rendring any reason for the same, the House of <hi>Vaux</hi>-hall being then upon sale, and since sold; but the like Orders would not serve to purchase the said house at an under rate, till it was turned into an Act; I know no reason but the like in due time may be for the said goods, and in the mean time, I hope they will be safe kept from imbezlement for the poor Creditors, whose goods indeed they are, though at present many of them want bread.</p>
            <p>Another for the sum of 2800 li. due from the Earl of <hi>Strafford</hi> deceased, as the like sum of money by him received in <hi>Ireland</hi> for the late Kings use in <hi>anno.</hi> 1639. or thereabouts, and was to be returned into <hi>England,</hi> and is not in charge in the Exchequer, for the which sum a near Kinsman of his is ingaged by a deed under his hand and seal to see the same satisfied out of the said Earls E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state in <hi>Ireland,</hi> the King pardoning the said Earls Estate forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for Treason, which was accordingly done, and the person so ingaged hath Received of the said Earls Estate in money, plate, hangings, and other goods, to many thousands of pounds, and yet that debt is unsatisfied.</p>
            <p>Another for the <hi>Georges</hi> and Garters due from the Knights of the Garter, as received upon their Installment from the King, who by their Oaths taken upon their Installment, as also by the Satutes and constitution of the said Order, are bound to take care that at their death their Executors do return the Robes to the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118388:7"/>and the Iewels to the King the donor.</p>
            <p>There are divers other great sums of money appearing due to the late King before the War from severall Receivers and Treasu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, for the Composition Provision due from the Country, for great sums of Money raised for the erecting a new Corporation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>London,</hi> some thousand of pounds being in particular hands, und unaccounted for to the late King; as also great sums due as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid, which was to be for a stock for the said Corporation, not yet accompted for; &amp; for great sums of money in particular hands raised as the Tax of Shipmoney, all which things in themselves being illegall and grievous to the People, and were therefore made Null, yet neverthelesse the said Receivers and Treasurers ought to accompt and satisfie for the same, there being no reason why they should have imployed it to their own use all this time, much lesse any longer to detain it, especially when so many hundreds of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are ready to starve through want of their just debts, due as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid.</p>
            <p>These and divers others have been made known by the said Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors unto the Trustees aforesaid, and some proceedings have been made therein, but most of them falling either upon Parl. men, or their friends, and relations, who day after day came sometimes 2.3. or more together to the Trustees, and pleaded for their friends, as Councel that had taken a Fee, but when they saw that would not prevail, they banded their forces together, and obtained a Committee to be erected by Order of Parliament, called the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee to examine abuses of Officers, &amp;c with power to stay pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, many of themselves being in effect parties and Iudges, and therefore some of them like a powerfull Sea carried all before them, upon all occasions, pleading against the interest of the said Creditors, more than the Plaintiffs Councel, often silencing the Councell for the Creditors, and not permitting the Trustees to speak indeed as if a Iudge had but one ear: whereupon a learned Councel well observing, said, Vnless the Creditors could interest themselves in the major part of the Committee, it was impossible to carry any businesse there. So that at last the said Creditors were taken off from any hopes of relief, untill God was pleased to give this present opportunity, which if wisely followed, through Gods assistance, may give a happy and speedy relief.</p>
            <p>I therefore propound as an expedient, that the said Creditors do
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118388:7"/>unanimously joyn together, peaceably to present to the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity whom God hath set over us, their sad and grievous suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, with the occasion thereof, and pray by way of Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That all the goods belonging to the late King, Queen, Prince, and Children yet unsold, may by the Trustees and Contractors for that purpose appointed, be forthwith exposed to sale, except the 10000 li. of the said goods to be reserved by virtue of the said first Act for uses of State, and that such their reserve, may be speedily effected, and that the goods in <hi>Whitehall</hi> Garden and elsewhere, which are sold to severall of the Creditors, be forthwith delivered to them that bought the same,</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the said second List being satisfyed the money in Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rear thereupon, the Trustees may be impowred to make a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable satisfaction to the Creditors and Servants, qualified according to the said Act of Parliament in that behalf made, out of the remainder of the said goods, who as yet have receivd no part of their debts, in such manner and such proportion as in their wisdoms may seem meet for the present relief of the said Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That in lieu of the 26500 li. lent for the use of the Navy, out of the product of the said goods, that the Power of the said Trustees may be inlarged to supply, wherein the said additionall Act is wanting, for the better prosecuting of the said discoveries slice and manner, as in their wisdom shall be most agreeable to lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in such Reason.</p>
            <p>And that they may have a like Cognisance, as by the said Act is appointed, to such a sum as may make the said 28000 pound ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away from the said Creditors in ready money, with the goods which shall be discharged, sufficient to pay the debt due to the said Servants and Creditors.</p>
            <p>This I hope may be the rather granted, in that no private person can by Law as an Executor or Administrator, dispose of the goods and personall estate of the deceased, untill his debts are first satisfied.</p>
            <p>By all which it sufficiently appeareth, that the delay and want of satisfaction hath been occasioned by them, who contrary to the Act of Parliament of <hi>June</hi> 1649. have taken from the use of the said Creditors and Servants 2800 l. in ready money, and about
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118388:8"/>40000 l worth of the best of the goods, and afterwards gave order to the Trustees and Contractors, to cause satisfaction to be made of the sums contained in the payed List; indeed an <hi>Egyptian</hi> task, instead of bread to give the hungry a stone. For by the first Act of Parliament to promise the people fair, and give a seeming power to the said said Trustees, but afterwards by delays and other pretences, to take away all the effects which should satisfie the said Creditors, whereby many of the said Creditor, who have there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon continually clamored against the said Trustees, as if they had had wherewith to satisfie them withall, and would not; As also it appeareth, that the prosecutiō of discoveries hath occasion'd many reproaches, scandals, clamors, disobligations, and vexations upon the said Trustees, Divers men then in authority being accounta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and not obtaining their desires from the said Trustees in such cases, did therefore, as is before expressed, take occasion upon the unreasonable clamors of many of the said Creditors &amp; Servants, to obtain the Erecting of the said Committee meerly to save them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves; for who can expect Iustice, where the offendor is Iudge?</p>
            <p>Indeed, upon the whole matter, the said Trustees have had the worst imployment that ever honest men had, that Acted by Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Parl. it being altogether impossible, that having to do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween men in Authority, who had not only power, but occasion themselves to the use or the goods, and the produce of that which should releeve so many hundreds of necessitous people, but that there must necessarily follow many disobligations, hazards, vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, reproaches, and clamors without end, all which their inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency maketh them willing to bear.</p>
            <p>Yet neverthelesse the said Trustees, Contractors and Treasurers, are now ready, for the vindication of their innocency against all aspersions whatsoever, to give a just and perfect account of every pennyworth of the goods, and many which by vertue of the said Acts of Parliament have come to their hands, to have been duely and truly disposed of according to the said Acts of Parliament, and shall leave the vindication of their proceedings to those whosoever shall receive the same.</p>
            <p>And as to a Complaint made by several of the said Creditors and Servants, touching an advance of 10 l. in the hundred for the goods which they did receive, and that the goods so received did produce so little; To that I answer, That the whole matter was
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118388:8"/>upon occasion of their complaint examined by the aforesaid Committee for Complaints, and by them dismissed by an order of Vindication, it appearing to them that the persons who did so ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance, had goods for the same, as well as their debts, and that the said advance was the voluntary Act and desires of many hundreds of the said Creditors, as may appear by a paper subscribed under their hands, and that the money so raised, was not any part there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of disposed to the use of the said Trustees, but that above 2000 l. in money, more than what was so raised by advance, and paid to the Treasurers, was by them issued forth to above 400 poor men, widdows and orphans, towards the satisfaction of their debts; and that the said goods did produce so little as 7 or 8 sh. in the pound: the reason whereof I refer to indifferent men, to consider the Cause why the most valiant and deserving Souldiers arrears, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chased with so much blood, and being altogether as just a debt, and the Commonwealth (if possible) more obliged for the true payment thereof; and the rather, in that the members thereof now peaceably enjoy their lives, liberties, and estates, as the fruit of their blood: yet neverthelesse many thousands of the said soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, not being any longer able to subsist, have sold their arrears for 6.5.4.3.2. and sometimes for one 1 shil. in the pound. And many of the said Creditors (who do most complain against the said Trustees) well know, how their affections and endeavours have been contrary to the interest of this Commonwealth, as may be particularly made appear if occasion shall offer, and that the late King payed to them after the rate of 1200 l. for divers parcels of the said goods, which are now apprized only at 400 or 500 l, and were scarce at all used in his service.</p>
            <p>These and many other things, both towards the disposition of diverse of the said Creditors and Servants, and also concerning the nature of their said Debts, might be here inserted, both for further manifesting of the Trustees sufferings, and vindicating of their persons and actions from all aspersions either in print or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise, but I hope these at present may suffice, yet as further occasion shall offer it self, I shall enlarge. In the mean time, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire the Charitable Reader patiently to consider what I have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and to satisfie himself that the Cause thereof was not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach any mans person: all which I have here avoided as much as possibly I could, but to show the particular reasons, as at first
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118388:9"/>I undertook, how it came to passe that the said Creditors and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of the late King, Queen, and Prince have been subjected to so great miseries, and the rather, in that I well know it is impos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible that they, much lesse any indifferent persons, should imagine that the supreme men in authority of this Nation, should so con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict their own act, word, or action, even to the ruine of so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hundreds of poor men widdows and orphans, whose whole means of livelyhood dependeth thereon.</p>
            <p>And considering that their demeanour, under such grievous af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, is somewhat the more clamorous, in that such speedy changes do immediatly succeed such prosperous times of enjoying their places, and because oppression, (which driveth them into these necessities and extremities) is enough to make wise men mad; and that calamities are far easier to see in others, than to feel, bear, or suffer our selves, yet I could wish that they would adde a little more patience to their further diligence, and lay all the blame at the doors of those that deserve it, and learn so much discretion, as to discern friends from enemies, and above all, to joyn all their endeavours, unanimously, peaceably, and lovingly to promote this great work, which so much tendeth to the supple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all their outward necessities; seeing God of his undeser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved mercy hath now once more offered unto them such a precious occasion, and excellent opportunity, in order to the satisfaction of all their just desires, which (I suppose) if it should be neglected, can neither easily nor speedily be recovered.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>